welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
check-ins 5% nervous a little like
giggly like a boyish giggle eNOS if I
can use if I can make up that word so
yeah welcome to the stoah my name is
Peter Lindbergh I'm the Stewart of the
stoah and the still has a place for us
to cohere and dialogue about what
matters most at the knife's edge of this
moment and today was interesting because
we just organically a bunch of events
emerged that either had jordan
Peterson's name in it or were directly
about Jordan Peterson so I thought you
know what let's just put the title of
suppose IAM on the series of events and
then you know with a little bit of
cuteness
we called it let us maybe get triggered
by Jordan Pederson symposium so for
those of you who are new at the store
because we have about seventy people
RSVP'd and the book 46 are here right
now
full disclosure Jordan Peterson was my
therapist for two years before he became
a superstar famous superstar so I have a
great love for him but this does not
mean I agree with everything he said it
says it's needless to say but I do think
it's interesting to have more important
and interesting to have a conversation
about some of the ideas he's presented
and I was talking to Raven it feels
tone-deaf having this with all these
riots going on in America but a lot of
this has been booked before what was
happening some sensitive to that and
mindful of it as well and so Raven is
going to be R and C for the day and she
can introduce herself introduce today's
speaker and how it's going to go down
and then after this event at 4:00 p.m.
Eastern Time we have a myth and mayhem
leftist critique adjourned Peterson from
the people who had the dr. Jordan
Peterson CIA team and at 6:00 p.m. we
have the filmmakers of the the rise of
durin Peterson we're gonna be screening
in a sense making session and then a
cure that dawn it's gonna come in that's
8:30 p.m. Eastern Time he's gonna have a
meeting wave session so you're gonna Jam
listening to Jordan Peterson and awesome
music so that means that I'm going to
hand it over to everyone's favorite
blackbird raven connolly thank you Peter
yeah it was interesting because with
with the riots going on I
I felt like actually having Chloe here
was almost the perfect person to open up
the symposium to draw in the wisdom of
Jordan Peterson and the theory of
Enchantment as it relates to the current
political and spiritual crises that
we're seeing right now on the streets of
America and so I feel like deeply
honored and and grateful that we made
this we made this arrangement for you to
come on today and talk about the theory
of Enchantment and how it relates to the
current crises that we have going on
right now so thank you so much Chloe for
being here
deeply appreciate it if you would like
to of course and if you would like to
introduce yourself sure hi everyone my
name is Chloe Valerie I am 26 years old
I created a startup called theory of
Enchantment roughly a year ago and the
purpose of the startup is really to
teach people how to build character and
to develop character amidst the chaos
and complexity of the human condition
so can we I wanted to go through the
three main principles of the theory of
Enchantment and relate those to what
you're seeing right now on the streets
of our country so the first one if you
don't mind if I read it sure we are
human beings not political abstractions
yeah that's a big one there's a reason
and I tweeted about this this morning
there's a reason why that's the first
principle cuz it's foundational and if
people don't understand this and people
don't internalize this and really Center
this principle in their activism and in
their understanding about how to sustain
democracy then there will be challenges
and there will be a great deal of
trouble and I think we're seeing that
right now with regard to some of those
who have hijacked a lot of the protests
within the streets of America people are
unfortunately some people are you know
adopting very dehumanizing language in
the way that they're protesting they're
saying you know F white people at the
police and so they're weather
essentially doing is they are reducing
individuals human beings to certain
abstractions whether that's an
abstraction based on race whether that's
an abstraction based upon a uniform that
a man or woman wears and as a result
they are obscuring the fact that these
people are human beings who are and and
you know we asked a question in the
course in the theory of a time of course
what does it actually mean to be human
it means that you are imperfect it means
that you are flawed it means that you
are multi-dimensional which means you
have the capacity to do good and the
capacity to do evil and this capacity
exists within every single one of us and
so if one is not cognizant of this one
can lose themselves in their activism
one can end up becoming the very thing
that they seek to to overcome and this
is really an inflection point in our
country's history and a moment where we
have to make sure that we don't do that
and we don't fall into the nihilistic
chaos of saying you know well
everything's hopeless anyway and we're
never gonna change anything so we should
say screw it and tear it all down
because the fact of the matter is that
what it also means to be human is to be
able to rise above your circumstances is
to be able to maximize your full
potential and it's to be able to have
the necessary emotional and spiritual
maturity to overcome seemingly
insurmountable odds that's also what
makes being human special and the human
condition is special so it's very very
important that people understand that
first place you go absolutely the second
principle criticized to uplift and
empower never to tear down or destroy so
yes obviously also this is a very it's a
very very appropriate principle for
what's happening right now but it's it's
it's for both
a person being criticized and also the
person doing the creek or doling out the
criticism and this this was sort of
relates to my understanding of of the
way the world works
I should back up for a bit I should say
the theory of Enchantment the uniqueness
of it is that I use both the
developmental psychology and pop culture
to teach it and I think this is where I
sort of overlapped with a lot of what
Jordan Peterson does because obviously
you know in maps of meaning for example
he brings in Pinocchio and he brings in
many of the great myths of cultures from
all around the world to really create a
framework an ethical framework and
that's what I tried to do as well and so
the second principle is very much
related to my belief in the fact that
the central teaching in the Lion King
which is about the circle of life which
is about how we are interconnected to
each other which is about how if I do
something wrong it doesn't only affect
you it affects the people that you
effect it affects tenfold beyond myself
and so the second principle is not just
about rooting our intentions in a good
place when we criticize others because
that's important and I think that's a
morally sound position but it's also
about the fact that if you don't do that
you actually end up compounding the
situation right so if you see someone
engaging in bad behavior right this is a
perfect perfect example for our current
time if you see a police in uniform
engaging in bad behavior first of all
you know nothing about the individual in
the uniform you don't know if this
person was in war at one point and had
PTSD and had unhealed PTSD and is now in
the police force right you don't know
anything about the background of this
person you don't know anything about the
baggage of this person you don't know
anything about the wait so that this
person is carrying the only thing that
you know about this person is the moment
that you are experiencing with this
person and so if you see or if you hear
of someone engaging in in unjust actions
what you should not do is criticize that
person in such
way that tears them down you want to
make sure or your criticism is rooted in
a way that lifts and uplifts everyone
involved and this is something that dr.
King taught you know obviously in his
ideas about how to create the Beloved
Community um but what you end up doing
if you don't do this if you compile the
situation because if you tell someone
and Maya Angelou talked about this if
you tell someone they're nothing over
and over again they will say to you oh
you think I am nothing I will show you
where nothing is and then they will
become even worse than what you have
accused them of being and the moral of
the story is that a person cannot
develop character unless they are valued
and this seems counterintuitive because
if someone is acting incorrectly toward
you personally it's very hard to say to
yourself oh I'm gonna criticize you and
I'm going to correct you not only
because what you are doing is unjust but
I'm also going to correct you because I
care about you I'm also going to correct
you because I know that you have more
potential than what you are doing right
now I'm going to speak to that potential
and I'm going to speak to your capacity
to rise to your higher self it's very
difficult to do that which really I
think sort of illustrates how truly
radical the civil rights movement was
because as a reminder people during the
civil rights movement literally studied
stoicism right and trained themselves
not to fight back when desegregating
diners and the purpose of this was to
fold some of strategic perspectives if
the state is using repressive force
against you and it creates an image of
violent state versus nonviolent peaceful
protesters about the the the scales in
terms of moving public opinion towards
civil rights tips in your favor as a
nonviolent protest that's number one
remember - from a spiritual perspective
and from a moral perspective the idea
was we are going to embody the
principles we seek to facilitate in this
society so we
cannot drag down another human being
even as we are criticizing their wrong
behavior and we recognize that if a
person is caught up and engaged in wrong
behavior they are also trapped in that
wrong behavior so we speak to the again
the possibility of human beings and this
is the nature of the human condition
to rise above not only other situations
but to rise above the immoral behavior
that they're engaging in
at the present moment so that's really
the the the idea behind the second
principle and the third principle lead
with love and compassion yes so this is
sort of the culmination of the theory of
Enchantment very much like the second
principle inspired by dr. King and dr.
King's philosophy of agape love and
using agape love which is a concept that
originates from Christianity and really
is all about this idea that you love a
person simply because they were made in
the image of God and you love a person
simply because they are a human being
you do not love a person because of
their behavior you do not love a person
because you agree with every single
thing that they do but be cut but
because simply there are human being and
and by rooting everything you do in love
and compassion again you embody the
values that you wish to see perpetuated
in society and one of the things that I
love to teach or to use as a tool for
teaching this particular concept in the
theory of entrapment sort of lexicon is
a pop culture favorite of mine which is
the story of Moana so mallanna is one of
the great I personally think it's one of
the greatest Disney movies certainly in
contemporary times ever made but
mallanna is and for those of you who
haven't seen it I'm gonna talk to you a
little bit about it but so this is a
spoiler alert be still watch it because
it's an amazing show but what's
brilliant about Moana is that Moana
differs from many of the other Disney
heroes so a lot of the Disney heroes go
through the classic hero's journey that
folks like Jordan Peterson described in
maps of meaning so the hero has to
encounter a bunch of obstacles and this
transformed
by the encountering of that obstacle and
the hero sort of has flaws also
obviously and have to transcend those
flaws but mallanna is a very different
kind of hero mallanna is simply a healer
she's literally from the time she is
born she was put on earth to heal that
is her that is her life's purpose and so
I'm just gonna explain the context a bit
for you and I promise I will draw I'll
draw this to something that's happening
in real life so Moana the the story goes
that mallanna is on an island and the
island is dying and the reason why the
island is dying is because there was a
goddess ruled over this island named to
Fiji and to Fiji was green and lush and
made everything beautiful everything
flourished but then the heart was taken
from Tahiti and in her place arose a new
goddess named touka and sakal was full
of lava and fury and rage and some of
the impulses that were witnessing right
now in the streets of america and so the
the goal the objective of mallanna is to
restore the heart of to Fiji to defeat
to come restore the heart look to think
about that is what the film is about now
at the very end and again you should
still watch it at the very end when
mallanna confronts touka
again imagine it's this lava rageful
goddess just destroying everything right
cuz the island she's making the island
die so she's holding a heart of to fiji
in her hand and she looks at the car and
she has his aha moment that she hadn't
had in the rest of the film and in the
movie the water sort of alive and her
her friend or whatever and so there's a
body of water separating Takei I'm Ilana
I'm Alana tells the water let her come
to me and so the water disperses very
much like a like a Moses moment and so
Takei starts to come again full of rage
full of fury
Malala starts to
talk to her very very calm like a little
too calm considering the situation
they're very calm and she says to her a
very simple thing she says I have
crossed the horizon to find you I know
your name they have stolen the heart
from inside you but this does not define
you and the aha moment that she has when
she says this and all of a sudden two
consoles like stops the aha moment that
she has was that the car and so fitti
were the same exact being so when the
heart was removed from two feet he/she
descended into rage and into destruction
and truck and started destroying
everything mana is a is a commentary on
the on the need for spiritual
nourishment within human beings and so
once mallanna returned the heart to Kyle
once more became to Fiji again and this
relates to the first principle right we
had the capacity to do good we have the
capacity to do evil it was the same
exact me the same exact thing but to
Copic bTW because the heart was removed
and obviously the heart is a motif for
love and compassion because the heart
was removed she descended into rage and
I think that's what we're seeing right
now I'm in this country there is a lack
of spiritual ratification there's a lack
of basic this is a basic idea of love
and compassion for your fellow neighbor
when it acts well then if you're a cop
or that's the peak of the community that
you're policing but if you're a citizen
that's for all the people in your
neighborhood including the cops that are
policing your neighborhood there's a
lack of love and compassion and we are
seeing the negative effects of that
right now I'm going to tell you one more
story sort of round this out about love
and compassion at the University of
Florida a few years ago there was a
neo-nazi that came to speak and there
was a protest that ensued outside of the
room no there was a God
named cuz I'm was front Randy furnace
Randy furnace at the time identified as
a neo-nazi he had Nazi signs all over
his t-shirt it was no you know guess who
he was there to see but in order to get
to don't see this person you had to walk
through the sea of protesters right now
when he got to the sea of protesters
some of them started pushing him shoving
him spitting on him cursing him out
one person punched him in the face
causing blood to draw until another man
african-american man sees Randy furnace
and has no idea what to do he's seeing
for the first time someone who hates him
because of his skin color has no idea
what to do and so for some reason in
that move in that moment he does the
only thing he's moved to do which is to
say that he hugs him and he pulls him
close and he asked him the question
three times why do you hate me why do
you hate me
why do you hate me and at this point
ready furnace doesn't know what to do
because the object of his hatred is now
hugging him it's not exactly what he
expected and so in that moment he's done
he's moved to do the thing that comes to
him which is to say he hugs him back and
he simply responds by saying I don't
know in this exchange sparks a series of
conversations between between Randy
furnace and the other guy's name is
Aaron Courtney and other members of the
african-american community and Randy
furnace has since disavowed his ties to
neo-nazi movement now what's interesting
about this is if you were to look into
randy furnaces background you would
learn that he was suicidal in his
twenties early 20s and from from the
perspective from where i'm standing that
makes perfect sense because if your
sense of self-worth is so empty that you
are willing to kill yourself or attempt
to kill yourself
then you can be easily exploited by
other groups that are going to give you
a cause with which you can derive
meaning from right and so I tell you
that story because
and Courtney Lee with love and
compassion instead of the the the
impulse that the crowd led with and it
was almost as if when Aaron saw him it
was almost as if he had a similar moment
that mallanna had it was almost as if he
said to him I have crossed the horizon
to find you I know your name they have
stolen the heart from inside you but
this does not define you so we have to
somehow find a way it's a central love
and compassion in our discourse to
Center in the in the protests that we're
seeing it has to be holistic it has to
spread it has to be universal it has to
be love for the black community and love
for the white community it has to be
love for citizens and love for police
officers it has to be holistic it has to
be consistent otherwise it will not work
so I want to invite people to begin to
put their questions in the chat so if
you just type it out and then I'll call
on you to ask your question to Chloe so
Chloe you've already told a few stories
that I feel like have a lot of wisdom
for the current moment but are there
other stories that you can think of
maybe talk about the Pinocchio story or
stories that you learn from from Jordan
Peterson or maps of meaning that have
some salient truths that can lead us to
a path of redemption or hope for
transcendence of this current moment
yeah that's a good question so actually
a couple months ago when Kovac started
happening I watched maps of meaning 2017
version and I'm actually reading Matson
meaning now which is something so it's
definitely a tour de force in terms of
stories that that Jordan Peterson has
told that really resonate with me I
think yeah when he broke down Pinocchio
you know I watched Pinocchio first and
then I watched his analysis and it it's
crazy to me because the thing that
stands out about Pinocchio that most
people know what Pinocchio for is the
fact that when he lies his nose extends
right which is like the least important
and least interesting ass
facts of Pinocchio one of the things
that really stuck out to me was Jordan
Peterson's explanation of when Pinocchio
was carted off to Pleasure Island
because I think we're seeing parallels
of that with regard to some of the
hijackers of the protest when when
Pinocchio was carted off to Pleasure
Island and was encouraged by the
stagecoach to basically weak havoc to
destroy they were him and sort of the
other boys were encouraged to destroy a
home to just throw bricks into the it's
like crazy how much of a one-to-one
correlation there is here but they were
encouraged to just just sort of evolved
into nihilistic frenzy and destroy
everything because nothing mad is the
only thing that matters is what's
immediate the only thing that matters is
your feeling of pleasure
right in this moment right and that's
why it's called Pleasure Island but of
course it was all a con because the
stagecoach was involved in a sinister
plot - slowly but surely change these
young boys into literal donkeys and to
cart them off into slavery and it is an
incredible metaphor for what happens
when we lose ourselves so the base
instincts that we have within us because
we do have have those impulses within us
when we lose ourselves and when we are
not capable of controlling ourselves we
turn into slaves essentially and it's so
ironic because this is this is a you
know we're talking about right now in
the country a cause that is first and
foremost trying to advance principles of
Liberty right how do we bring about
justice and police forces how do we
ensure that police officers understand
that the the demand to protect and to
serve applies not only to would-be
victims but also the criminals that you
have in your in York they are under your
concern they're under your jurisdiction
the moment you arrest them you also have
an obligate
to protect and serve them as well even
though you obviously have to do your
duty and get them into into a specific
place and so this question is how do we
pursue justice how do we actually create
a society that is rooted in Liberty and
yet we have people who are descending
into madness and descending into
lawlessness and becoming slaves to their
own passions and becoming slaves to this
impulse and this instinct to be
nihilistic so that's a philosophically
inconsistent and morally inconsistent
way to bring about justice and I think
that the Pinocchio story um really
really sort of promotes that and that
idea and really shows that idea but the
other thing that it shows and and this
is also true I think of Sleeping Beauty
which I also rewatched recently is that
the hero has to make sacrifices and is a
hero's job to basically look chaos in
the eye and create order out of it and I
think that this is also the artists task
right it's to create meaning out of just
destruction and chaos and malevolence
that is the Bettis the job of the artist
that it's the job of the hero that is
the job of the leader I'm I wrote a
newsletter or I published a newsletter
today that release was studying the
movie Black Panther actually because I
think I think Black Panther has
incredible wisdom for this moment right
now in our in our country because it
juxtaposes two different sets of
principles within the characters of King
T'Challa and kill monger kill monger is
killer was abandoned he's the villain he
was abandoned he was left to rot he was
neglected and so what happens he
internalizes that sense of abandonment
he internalizes that sense of neglect
and he rages and he becomes destructive
and he becomes homicidal and suicidal
you know he destroys everything
everything that comes before him even
from his ancestors right and T'Challa
was the king
the rightful king has to say to his
father what you did when you abandoned
him was was horrible like you this is a
monster of our own creation right I'm
sorry acknowledges the rage that kill
monger halves and acknowledges the sense
of despair that he has but it also says
but this is not the way this is not the
way if you have malice in your heart and
hatred in your heart you are unfit to be
king and that is the one of the most
prominent lessons within black panther
so the so the hero is able to correct
his father's his father's a rule so
tradition when tradition doesn't work or
tradition needs to be updated right this
is something that Jordan Peterson talks
about a lot when the tyrant father needs
to sort of be updated in terms of how he
behaves you have to have the hero which
is the birth of both tradition and chaos
right so the new and the old coming
together to create a new and better
balance and that's what the child
represents and and that's why he has to
make sure that kill monger doesn't
doesn't usurp but that's some of the
ways in which Jordan Peterson in
particular and a lot of pop culture in
general has influenced my work awesome
thank you and we've got some really
great questions coming up the chat I'd
like to start with Frank's question so
Frank if you'd like to unmute yourself
and ask your question to Chloe thank you
David
hi Chloe so I've been following you on
Twitter for awhile and I find your
perspective quite refreshing so my
question for you is very straightforward
why is it called the theory of
Enchantment why enchantment so so great
question background information on how
the theory of Enchantment developed I
was at the Wall Street Journal for a
year in 2015 I was working on a thesis
paper my background and from from a
college perspective is conflict
resolution these are V like
International Studies I was working on a
paper on this topic and there was no you
know there was all this
how to get people to stop conflict which
is to say how do you get people to stop
hating and I realized that there was no
framework within International Studies
to ask the question of how do you get
people to start loving and these two are
not the same questions they're
interrelated questions but they're not
the same questions and I wanted to
create a framework back teaches people
how to love and so then I thought to
myself well what if I ask what are
people already in love with and then use
that to create a framework for teaching
people how to love and the thing that
people were in love with was pop culture
and so I then started to study pop
culture so see if there was a common
denominator cause various different
influencers and companies and
celebrities terms of the content that
they were producing but there was a
theme I've studied companies like Nike I
studied artists like Beyonce
I studied companies like Disney and the
common denominator was all these
entities and influencers are creating
content where their audience sees
themselves and their potential reflected
in the content and that's why we buy it
and so you know Disney played a huge
role actually ultimately in informing my
decision to make it to call it
enchantment but the real source of why I
called it enchantment was because of a
book I read called
enchantment by Guy Kawasaki was the
former marketing director of Apple and
he defines enchantment as the process by
which you delight someone with a concept
with an idea or what just you know your
own personality and I found that idea of
delight very intriguing and very much a
beautiful thing because he's when I
think of delight when I think of
enchantment I think of this concept of
wonder and I think that one of the
things were losing and our societies in
the West is our sense of wonder and this
is related to the fact that we're not
we're no longer speaking we're not we're
no longer talking in a way that speaks
to people's potential right that's all
that's all related potential Wonder
delight enchantment love these are these
are words that are missing increasingly
from our vocabulary and so to call it
enchantment
what's really my attempt to try to bring
some to bring those ideas back into the
fold
so I'm based in India and we have
messenger as well so yeah beautiful
answer thank you thank you Jacob would
you like to ask your question yeah so uh
since you're talking a lot well this is
all about Jordan Peterson right so it
made me think of me chase Hammer
he took a hammer to things and so and
then the wisdom of Solomon says there's
a time to tear down and a time to build
up so you said never tear down maybe you
don't mean never but if you do mean
never then it seems like well heavy
appeared here's the question sure have
you considered the need for a
distinction between tearing down the
person so ad hominem tear down tearing
down the idea and tearing down the
behavior because it seems like those
things need to be parsed before we say
never tear down right yeah no I
definitely those distinctions I
definitely mean don't dehumanize I think
that's ultimately what I mean so so
again going back to the example of the
leadership those involved in the civil
rights movement
one of the animating principles behind
non-violence in the attempts to
desegregate the diners was based upon
this concept of not dehumanizing anyone
including your enemy because then you
create or you contribute to a society
that is unjust even in the name of
justice
so by tear down I don't mean this man I
don't mean don't dismantle systems of
oppression but I am arguing that it's
hard and nearly arguably impossible to
dismantle a system of oppression if you
are being oppressive in your language
and if you're being dehumanizing toward
your enemies so that is the distinction
that I would make I hope that that is
somewhat satisfied all right so next
question here I climb I really enjoy the
this as an ethical basis what I what I
would struggle to imagine is how to
apply this or I'm just interested in
your tactics and like applying these
ethics to everyday interactions with
family and with friends who it's
difficult to kind of mirror there to not
mirror their confrontational attitudes
like how do you apply this on a ground
level well I can tell you that I
personally have done a lot of self work
so so the clear of interment course is a
full twenty five lesson course and the
first part the first one-third of the
course is working on the self and so
before you talk about how to have a
healthy relationship with other people
the primary question is how you have a
healthy relationship with yourself which
means understanding yourself again as I
said earlier
human being becoming comfortable with
your imperfections not overcompensating
for them learning about your baggage not
overcompensating for them understanding
that there are certain emotions that
inform your behavior so for example I
know that when I am feeling insecure I
may sometimes act defensive and so just
understanding that about myself
I think equips me and positions me in
such a way to be able to deal with
others because if I know for example
that if I am feeling insecure I am
defensive then when people let's say
when a family member is randomly
seemingly randomly
acting defensive toward me and I don't
understand why it could be the case that
they are feeling insecure right and so
then I will modify my response being
cognizant of the fact that there's an
emotional baggage that's informing the
behavior it's it's it's more in-depth
and so I would say the first step is you
have to this is what I have to work on
yourself and it's like a project like a
daily practice obviously I also meditate
for an hour a day and that really serves
to calm down my nervous system in
general and so yeah so just like trying
to practice some of the some of the
teachings in the theory of enchant first
applying them to the self and then
applying them to the other it's a
long-term strategy because people don't
I don't think one becomes you know about
able to to respond to confrontation with
a less aggressive stance overnight
that's just not how we're wired and so
it takes practice which is why you know
so we teach tourism in the theory of
Enchantment platform as well so stoicism
and practicing stoicism and trying to
remember principles like take the view
from above take the view from below
meditate on your mortality so that you
understand that these emotions that
you're experiencing right now are
totally fine emotions you can experience
the emotions but you also have to learn
to let the emotions pass right so these
are very again daily practices that I
work on and that students
jamming coursework on to then be able to
be in better relationships with their
with other members of their society that
doesn't mean obviously that you agree
because that's not the point
right you don't have to agree with with
everyone that you encounter but I think
the idea is to try and model that love
and compassion even in the midst of
profound disagreement thank you Jacob K
would you like to ask your question Oh
Jacob I can't hear you how about now is
this okay yep awesome yeah I found you
on Twitter like two days ago but this
shit you're putting out is really
high-quality so witnessing this big kind
of memetic wave kind of around the
blackout Tuesday on Instagram and
associated with that of a lot of people
mostly white friends putting their
willingness to listen and learn and then
I don't know if you're familiar with the
Evergreen State
yep thing okay that makes it easy so
kind of this unease that I'm feeling of
like well who-who is it that it's not
clear who's being listened to and what
it is that you're going to be learning
and then there's just the signaling of
your willingness to do it but it's not
clear what and like from what kind of
emotional state is that coming from yeah
I'm just feeling a lot of confusion
around that meme wave and also a sense
of like posting anything which is trying
to speak to that and kind of complexify
err is going to be very unwelcome sure
I'm inflamed I can tell you personally
that I
like this is just me personally I'm not
making a judgment call on others who
choose to do this I I think it's like I
don't really care about it you know
because it is it is a this mean thing
that's happening specifically today is a
I think it's I think it's confined
within a certain time time situation
it's it's gonna be on to the next
subject tomorrow you know I think it's
slightly performative i I do think that
a lot of people are coming from a
sincere place when they post these
things
I'm not everyone is but a lot of people
are and I acknowledge that sincerity I
honor that sincerity but I am a little
like that's just not me that's not what
I'm about I don't think that that's
meaningful really um I also am like
really weirded out by like white people
genuflecting and and doing a very
strange sort of like like tell us what
we should do because we are white and
you are black I find that very much
antithetical to this to the first of all
the point of the pursuit of justice and
to the spirit of the first principle of
the theory of Enchantment because the
idea that I have some sort of holy
knowledge merely because I am black is
silly and the idea that a white person
has nothing to contribute to the
conversation merely because they are
white is also silly because again this
is this is the whole human being some
political abstractions sort of situation
so that's just me that's like my that's
my natural response to it but I'm also
just not like I don't think it's
necessary to entertain everything that's
happening on social media especially
because it's here today and gone
tomorrow you know this I don't consider
this to be like this Instagram thing
like a movement on par with you know the
Arab Spring or something we remember in
history and I just I just think it's
sick
and and does not work my entertainment
it doesn't mean I'm gonna I'm not gonna
like speak out against it but I I'm I'm
more indifferent to it than anything
else thank you thank you
rain would you like to ask your question
you out there rain oh can you hear me
now yes okay
thanks sorry I'm I'm on my iPad and not
as familiar with it
there I am Thank You Chloe so
appreciating your stance and if someone
else said it's refreshing and I feel the
same way my question is one that I know
has been asked many times and I'm sure
there's some good thought on it but I
haven't really studied the civil rights
movement but just the question of if
you're really committed to this peaceful
form of protest what's to stop people
who have the power from simply ignoring
the peaceful protests so it's a great
question there's a study that came out
at Cambridge University I think last
week that demonstrated the how the
nonviolent protests of the civil rights
movement actually move the needle in
terms of public opinion compared as
compared to the violent protest sort of
the violent riots that took place in the
late 60s and what they found was that
first of all if whenever there's
violence there will be media attention
and so the reason why the nonviolent
protests move the needle is because of
the juxtaposition between state violence
and the peaceful protesters because it
was such a sharp dichotomy because it
was obvious like it was like obviously
and ironically clear which camp was
being civilized and which camp was being
uncivilized that actually helped push
the needle forward in terms of
public opinion so I think everything
we've seen with regard to media coverage
sort of almost guarantees that if there
is violence there will be there will be
coverage and we've because we've seen up
till now precedent of police forces
overdoing it in many many cases and with
regards to protests around the country
and we because we see in some places
state violence against peaceful
protesters
we know that the media is there the
media is gonna cover it so then then the
question becomes okay so what is the as
activists and as protesters how do we
compare ourselves given that we know
that in the past this is what moves the
push the public opinion forward how do
we compare ourselves and how do we not
only from a moral perspective obviously
but also from a strategic and tactical
perspective create this juxtaposing
image of uncivilised ie the state versus
civilized and so I think that that's
enough of a the reason to consider at
the very least comporting yourself as an
activist in that way because we have we
have precedent we have evidence that it
did work it did work in the past Thanks
and in just a quick follow-up I know
there's some evidence that in certain
contexts violent action affects change
and and do you do you think those have
you studied the research do you think
that those results are non
representative or have other negative
effects well I think it would depend
upon where it depends on so many factors
right it depends on when you say
violence that are you saying people are
getting beaten up are you saying stores
are being looted are you saying people
are destroying businesses and what so
what is what is the nature of the
violence number one and what is the goal
and so I would have to to be on like
seriously and honestly like grapple with
that question I would have to know more
specific details but I
do believe in thesis antithesis
synthesis right so so I I do understand
and sympathize with I actually received
this question today I was on a phone
call with Glenn Greenwald and I received
the question about the wisdom or lack
thereof of not people who are just being
nihilistic and you know looting stores
but people who sincerely feel rage and
despair and the question was well what
do I say to those people and I think my
answer was I've truly sympathize but I
do believe that if we as activists want
to create a just society we cannot
afford to descend into despair because I
don't know I don't know what happens
after that it's like what next
you know um and also it's obviously easy
for someone to call me a hypocrite if I
say that I believe in justice but I
don't apply justice consistently across
the board you know I think I think it's
easy to get caught up in in rage and
despair and in the middle of a protest
say eff white people but I also find
that fundamentally immoral right and so
I think we have to we have to try our
best to be our higher selves so but
again I'm definitely willing to grapple
with the impact of violent protests and
counter protests and and and I think I
don't think I'll necessarily have a
concrete answer to that but I'm
definitely interested in continuing
continuing to grapple with it thank you
Kaleo would you like to ask a question
oh yes I feel kind of bad for kind of
derailing the conversation I think was
gonna reckon and I just wanna say thanks
to Peter and Riven and Chloe for making
this happen so my question is can you
conceive of such a thing as like over
enchantment or hyper enchantment it
seems like today our problems like
access
rather than not enough it might be very
easy for people to find enchanting
characters online just hyperstimulated
themselves I never actually like kind of
outsource their lives to characters or
anything yeah I mean I I don't know that
I can control I think what I hope to do
is to inspire people to practice to
develop certain practices within their
life that enables them to fortify their
character and four to five strength of
character and to the extent that someone
is outsourcing that work to you know
just I don't know retweeting me then
they're not doing what I'm trying to
inspire to do them to do and that I
don't that might be my fault
actually I don't know that that would be
my fault I don't know the extent to
which we can say that you know we are
autonomous beings and some level we have
to take responsibility for our actions
and obviously what you're describing is
always a risk but all I can say is I
will try to do my best to inspire people
to do the work themselves which is why
theory of Enchantment is a course it's
an actual like rigorous course as
opposed to just you know a series of
tweets and retweets but no I think it's
a good point and I think I should I
should be on guard and not fall into the
trap and to check myself and to make
sure that I am you know inspiring people
to actually take action thank you I just
want to make it clear that I wasn't
suggesting that you're guilty of this
okay
great let's see here
we have a question about reading
suggestions
oh here's here's one from Benjamin that
he asked me to ask you sure
given that Peterson is controversial
have you had to deal with any
difficulties due to your appreciation
for his work have you had to defend your
appreciation if so what has worked also
what is the best way to support your
work boost your signal oh yes
so I'll just answer that one first and I
guess I can can I post in the chat
actually so here is Chapman's website so
you can check out a lot of our stuff the
course is up there and just our
philosophy and like approach to life in
terms of Jordan Peterson it's
interesting I actually haven't gotten
flack yet you know I'm sure that that
will come up at some point I was when I
was the moderator of questions for the
film premiere of the rise and fall tour
and Peterson so I actually know those
filmmakers and I was part of the
premiere here here in Brooklyn a couple
months ago in December and so even then
I didn't get any weirdly enough I didn't
I didn't get any flack I think that the
reason perhaps why I haven't gotten any
flack is because I think Jordan Peterson
comes you know from a long line of a
certain type of philosopher /
psychologist I've put in in the same
camp as Carl Jung and Joseph Campbell
and and and coming up on Leah for
example I actually think Camille Paglia
is kind of superior but don't beat me up
for that one but but I also bring in of
course a lot of pop culture and into the
conversations that I have when I'm
talking about Jordan Peterson and what's
funny enough is it's almost as if I'm
basically hacking the network and what I
mean by that is joining Peterson is very
much similar to and sometimes talks
about Joseph Campbell right obviously a
lot
his commentary when it can't when it
comes to LGBTQ rights is the most
controversial aspect of his work
ironically I think that's the least
important aspect of his work but when it
comes to his connection to folks like
Joseph Campbell and Carl Jung what's
interesting about this is if you were to
listen to let's say Oprah
Oprah's podcasts Oprah's podcast
mentions Joseph Campbell so many times
like Joseph Campbell is a part of her
universe and a part of her lexicon and a
part of the way she thinks and you think
about how popular both Oprah and and
Jordan Peterson are it's fascinating
because there's so much overlap right
and so my the way i hack the networks or
the thing is by threading the needle
right and and also by being seriously
engaged in the these ideas and like
really grappling with them and
questioning them and unpacking them and
disagree when this is there in agreeing
when necessary so it's very difficult
for people to and people can obviously
critique me and they do all the time but
it's very difficult for people to
disparage to be disparaging in their
criticism because I'm trying to
encourage people to stop doing that and
so it becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy
so I'm afraid I can't give you any
advice besides I decide just just being
sincere and authentically grappling with
Jordan Peterson's ideas but also
grappling with other people's ideas
would challenge her in Peterson I
thought his debate with jejak was quite
fascinating not wasn't really a debate
but it was quite fascinating um to see
you know a Marxist and and someone like
during Peterson really actually come to
come to form certain certain parts of
agreement I wasn't really expecting that
so yeah I mean that's that's all I have
for that question I'm sorry I'm sorry
that that's not as efficient as it could
be all right well we're coming to a
close here Chloe are there any final
words that you would like to leave us
with
we'll stay safe especially here in the
United States of America and I think
it's really important to understand that
oftentimes perception is reality and if
you perceive that things are hopeless
and you will act in a manner that
indicates that things are hopeless and
if you perceive that things are possible
and or as a reminder the human condition
demonstrates to us that we are capable
of overcoming our circumstances and
overcoming our situations and rising
above and I can't tell you the college
stories I know personally of you know
you know former neo-nazis disavowing
their ties to racist movements - you
want to talk about Rwanda where an
entire country decided to reconcile
itself with itself we often talk about
the things that human beings do that are
devastating and horrible but we don't
speak enough about the things that
humans human beings do that is
incredibly resilient and incredibly
transformative and I think we need to
put more of those images and more of
those stories out into the into the
forefront of our of our media outlets so
that this becomes a self-fulfilling
prophecy the thing about self-fulfilling
prophecies is that it could be a good
prophecy we sort of use that term in a
negative connotation but it can become a
good a good prophecy so I encourage you
to you know check out the theory of
entrapment platform and if I can be of
help or service any of you reach out to
me on Twitter I'm happy to have
conversations and engage not to the best
of my ability but other than that keep
hope alive as my dad as my dad likes to
say keep hope alive beautiful thank you
so much for being here Chloe I can't
think of a better way to have open the
symposium that's beautiful awesome
all right well I'm gonna tell us a
little bit about the upcoming events
that we have going on here at the stoah
so we have it at for myth and mayhem a
leftist critique of Jordan Peterson with
the team from dr. Jordan Peterson CA and
then later on we have the rise of Jordan
Peterson screening and sense-making with
the filmmakers and after that we have
the meaning wave party with the DJ Akira
the dawn and lots more things going on
this week as well so I hope you all can
join us for those events and we see the
stove as a gift for everyone in this
time of need and if you feel inspired to
make a gift you can visit us at the
stoma dot CA and thank you all everybody
awesome thank you guys
you
debrief five minutes straight sure
you're still recording